<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<base xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" type="string">
  <tags>
    <tag language="Português Brasileiro" />
  </tags>
  <strings>
    <string id="0skIST3E" text="Cortejo" />
    <string id="AdGdZX6X" text="When kingdoms in Calradia go to war, their armies have two basic offensive options. They can try to attack villages and lay waste to the countryside, damaging their enemy's prestige and economy. Or, they can try to seize and hold castles or towns, taking territory This second option can involve long, bloody sieges, but will yield more decisive results.^^It is important to note that the realms of Calradia do not field standing armies, which remain in the field as long as the ruler desires. Rather, Calradian realms are protected by feudal levies comprised of the major nobles and their individual retinues.  Sometimes, these nobles launch their own private attacks into enemy territory, but the most decisive events will usually take place when the great hosts are assembled. The kingdom's marshal, a noble appointed by the king, will summon the host before the campaign and lead them out to battle. However, he should be careful not to keep them in the field too long. Otherwise, the host will begin to disintegrate, as the vassals drift off to pursue their own business, and the army will be vulnerable to a counter-attack.^^For this reason, the rhythm of wars in Calradia often resemble the rhythm of a duel between two individual combatants. One side will gather its strength and seek to land a blow against the enemy's territory. If the marshal spends too little time gathering the vassals, he may not be able to do any real damage. If he spends too much time, then the campaign may end before it has even begun. A large realm will have an advantage over a smaller one, just as a brawny combatant has an edge over a smaller foe, but a realm's political cohesion can also be a factor, just as a fighter with great stamina can outlast her opponent. Sometimes, the armies of two realms will meet head on, resulting in a major battle in which both numbers and morale will decide the outcome.^^Kingdoms will have imperfect intelligence about their enemies. Attacking lords will need to frequently scout enemy territory to determine which fortresses may be vulnerable. An army defending its homeland will benefit from the alarms raised by castles and towns, which broadcast intelligence about enemy movements in the area. Such intelligence will be imprecise, however, particularly when it comes to numbers. A defending force which sets out to raise a siege or rescue a village may be able to overwhelm an unprepared attacker -- or it may miscalculate, and find that it is the one to be overwhelmed. Attackers, in turn, must be careful how far they advance into enemy territory, with aggressive marshals venturing further than cautious ones.^^Players will be expected to join in their faction's military campaign, either by joining the host, or by scouting ahead into enemy territory. Some players may find that their realm's marshal is too cautious, or too aggressive, for their tastes. In this case, they can intrigue with other lords to try to replace the marshal, or build support to become the marshal themselves.^^Most wars are of limited duration. A king who goes to war will, for the sake of honor, feel obligated to pursue the conflict for a short while. However, unless he is soundly beating his enemy. he may soon start looking for a way out of the conflict, lest he leave himself vulnerable to an attack by a third party. Calradia's rulers are keenly aware that today's ally may be tomorrow's enemy, and vice versa." />
    <string id="BRQ7bDnn" text="The realms of Calradia, although they represent different cultures, all adhere to the same basic political system: feudalism. Feudalism is based on the relationships between individuals: the oaths of loyalty given by a vassal to his or her liege. In exchange for this oath, the vassal will usually receive a fief, a parcel of land whose income will be used by the vassal to raise troops to support the liege in time of war. A liege also has an obligation to protect his vassals, and to treat them justly.^^This is how it works in theory, anyway. In practice, vassals will not always work in their factions' interests, particular as they are often quarreling with one another. Nobles have different personalities, and sometimes those personalities clash. Or, perhaps two nobles were once friends, but fell out over in the aftermath of a setback or a defeat -- or because they both were wooing the same lady. Jealousies will also surface as they vie for the favor of the king -- perhaps over newly conquered lands, or over who will be given the coveted office of marshal, the lord in charge of organizing large-scale campaigns.^^When one realm in Calradia makes war on another, the political unity of the each kingdom is as important as the quality or number of its soldiers in determining the outcome. In a cohesive kingdom, nobles will join together in a large force to sweep their opponents before them. In a kingdom divided by petty quarrels, lords will fail to respond to the marshal's summons, or drift away to attend to their own business if a campaign is not going well. A faction's political cohesion will also impact warfare when campaigns are not in progress. In a divided faction, lords will be less likely to join together on raids and patrols, and come to each other's defense.^^If it seems self-defeating for nobles to bicker and quarrel when the enemy is just over the horizon, keep this in mind -- ultimately, a noble's loyalty goes not to a particular faction or culture, but to himself and to his family. If a noble fears that his faction is collapsing, or if he is being neglected by his liege, he can usually find a reason to withdraw his oath of allegiance, and change sides. Players should keep this in mind, as they may find that there are opportunities to turn discontented former enemies into allies." />
    <string id="gRokgcKb" text="A player character in Calradia may choose to come from a variety of social backgrounds. This choice will affect not just his or her starting skills and equipment, but also the course of his or her career as an adventurer.^^War and politics in Calradia are traditionally dominated by male aristocrats. A nobleman player character may find that he is invited into this 'old boys' club' fairly quickly, but women and commoners may face a few extra hurdles on the way. If you choose to start the game as a male nobleman, you can think of it as the 'easy' setting. Starting as a noblewoman or a male commoner is somewhat more difficult, and starting as a female commoner is probably the most challenging way to begin a game.^^However, women have some starting advantages. Simply by taking up arms, a female warrior will draw attention to herself, and she may find that she can build up her reputation faster than a male. Also, it is traditionally easier for a woman to marry up the social ladder than it is for a man, and a woman may find she can gain more from a strategic marital alliance than her male counterpart.^^Finally, keep in mind that the game does not place any limits on the upward mobility of characters based on their background. Noble or common, male or female, married or unmarried -- anyone can rise to become ruler of all Calradia, if they are sufficiently brave, lucky, or resourceful." />
    <string id="JOXssNCY" text="Os jogadores podem querer se casar com uma das famílias nobres de Calradia. O casamento não é necessário para um jogador aumentar seu poder e crescer na hierarquia, mas fornece a oportunidade de melhorar sua relação com os senhores e estabelecer uma reivindicação ao trono.^^Os requisitos de casamento serão diferentes para homens e mulheres. Um personagem masculino geralmente precisará seguir um caminho tradicional de cortejo. Ele deve estabelecer uma reputação na sociedade aristocrática calradiana, se relacionar bem com os pais ou responsáveis ​​de sua noiva e depois cortejar a dama de acordo com os costumes locais. Se o jogador ficar impaciente, ele pode tentar usar um atalho - mas haverá consequências em suas relações com outros senhores.^^Um personagem masculino deve ter em mente que outros senhores competirão com ele pelos afetos das damas do reino. Além disso, os gostos de uma mulher são imprevisíveis, portanto, o jogador pode achar que o objeto de seu amor não o ama de volta. O romance, em Calradia, como em outros lugares, nem sempre prospera. É claro que o jogador pode recorrer a outros meios menos gentis de conquistar o coração de uma mulher, mas, novamente, isso terá um sério impacto em sua reputação.^^Para começar no caminho do cortejo, o jogador do sexo masculino deve tentar se envolver na vida social da aristocracia calradiana, participando de festas e torneios. Além disso, trovadores e poetas errantes podem servir como uma útil fonte de informações sobre os cortejos e as fofocas para manter o jogador atualizado. ^^Personagens femininas também podem se casar - mas elas devem ter em mente que a sociedade calradiana é muito tradicional e, como aventureiras, escolheram um caminho não convencional para uma mulher. Uma personagem feminina pode ter que procurar por um tempo até encontrar um senhor com a mente aberta o suficiente para se casar com ela.^^Pelo lado positivo, uma personagem feminina não precisa passar pelos elaborados rituais de namoro, e também pode ganhar mais com um casamento do que um personagem masculino. Para uma aventureira, o casamento pode ser um caminho rápido para o poder - e um personagem sem escrúpulos pode ser capaz de usar o marido como uma ferramenta para alcançar suas ambições." />
    <string id="LeT28DTV" text="Passado do Personagem" />
    <string id="nb2RUabH" text="A moral representa a capacidade e a disposição das tropas de um exército para reunir a resistência, coragem e disciplina necessárias para enfrentar o estresse da marcha e do combate. Não é a mesma coisa que a felicidade das tropas. As tropas de elite podem resmungar e lamentar-se sobre as dificuldades da campanha - mas, então, permanecem juntas quando as flechas começam a voar. Por outro lado, um comandante que dá a seus homens tudo o que eles querem pode achar que eles ficam macios e renunciam diante da investida do inimigo.^^ Morale's greatest impact is on a party's behavior in battle, determining how aggressively troops engage the enemy, and how likely they are to break and run if they perceive the tide of battle turning against them. Morale also affects a party's march speed, as a less motivated party will move more slowly, as the men are not pushing themselves to their physical limit, and pause more frequently, as it waits for stragglers to catch up. Finally, a party with very low morale will start to suffer desertions.^^ Some factors that affect morale are intuitive. For example, a charismatic commander with a reputation for winning battles can infuse his or her men with a sense of confidence. Leaders who give their men well ample and varied supplies of food, and pay them on time, demonstrate that they care about their troops' welfare, and are less likely to lead them into disaster.^^ Other factors are less intuitive -- particularly those related to a party's sense of group cohesion. In a small tight-knit party, for example, men will often fight hard against daunting odds to avoid showing cowardice before their comrades-in-arms. A large party on the other hand may see its cohesion strained, as the commander has less time to supervise the men, listen to their grievances, and resolve their disputes. Frequent battles will strengthen the bonds between men, while long periods without combat will see the troops become bored and quarrelsome.^^ The morale report, accessibly by hitting the 'reports' button will give the player a sense of the factors affecting his or her men's morale." />
    <string id="TCynamna" text="Campanhas Militares" />
    <string id="u0O9WGsH" text="Política" />
    <string id="UjL7jVYF" text="Moral" />
    <string id="VHGqFz6p" text="As cidades e vilas de Calradia precisam de uma grande variedade de bens para que suas populações continuem saudáveis ​​e produtivas. O primeiro, em importância, é a comida. Os grãos são a colheita básica de Calradia, mas as pessoas também precisam de gordura e proteína na forma de carne, peixe ou queijo. É preciso quase tanto trabalho para preservar a carne quanto para produzi-la, portanto o sal também é muito procurado. Depois da comida vem a roupa: lã pesada, roupas mais leves ou veludo de luxo. Por fim, as pessoas precisam das ferramentas de seu ofício: ferragens, cerâmica, artigos de couro e, é claro, armas, armaduras e cavalos para guerra.^^A maioria dos produtos agrícolas é produzida nas aldeias, enquanto os artesãos das cidades se especializam em produtos manufaturados ou artesanais, como tecidos ou ferragens. Além disso, diferentes recursos podem ser encontrados em diferentes partes do país. Consequentemente, a chave para a prosperidade em Calradia é o comércio - tanto entre as aldeias quanto as cidades, e entre as principais cidades.^^Enquanto o comércio fluir, os bens estarão disponíveis e acessíveis, com isso, a população de um centro será saudável e enérgica e os pessoas migrarão das regiões próximas. O centro produzirá mais, consumirá mais e contribuirá mais em impostos para seus senhores. Quando o comércio parar, cidades e vilarejos verão seus trabalhadores fugindo em busca de trabalho em outros lugares, deixando a atividade econômica à deriva. Portanto, é do interesse dos governantes proteger as rotas comerciais dos riscos da guerra e do banditismo. Um comerciante inteligente, no entanto, pode querer procurar cidades que ficaram isoladas das outras, pois assim, ele ou ela pode obter lucros exorbitantes com o desequilíbrio dos preços.^^Já que os aldeões geralmente planejam levar seus produtos ao mercado das cidades, os mercados das aldeias são lugares bastante calmos, onde os aldeões compram barato e vendem caro. Comerciantes sérios se restringem às cidades para obter lucro, embora alguns grupos possam decidir fazer uma parada rápida em uma vila para adquirir suprimentos.^^Caso o jogador queira saber sobre os fatores que afetam a prosperidade de uma região, ele pode falar com o líder da cidade local. Outras informações podem ser obtidas dos ambulantes, embora estes geralmente não saibam muito fora de seu comércio particular." />
    <string id="VS7K0rFg" text="Economia" />
  </strings>
</base>